Guide to the Whittaker Family Charles Dickens Manuscript Collection, 1831-2003
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Whittaker Family Charles Dickens Manuscript Collection
1831-2003
Whittaker Family (Collectors)
5.7 cubic feet (17 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, sheet music, playbills, artwork, ephemera, realia as well as other miscellany relating to Dickens and his work.
Biographical Note
Victorian writer Charles Dickens (1812-1870) was one of the most well-known celebrities of his day, and his work continues to appeal to a large and diverse audience. His popularity is evident in the myriad editions and re-interpretations of his novels and short stories, but also in the presence of Dickens and his characters in a wide array of material culture.
Scope and Content Note
The Whittaker Family Charles Dickens Manuscript Collection includes correspondence, sheet music, playbills, artwork, ephemera, realia as well as other miscellany relating to Dickens and his work. The variety of objects in various formats, styles and composition, created while Dickens was alive but also well after his death, illustrates the enduring popularity of the author's work. Of particular note are original watercolors by both Hablot K. Browne and Joseph Clayton Clarke ("Kyd").
For more information about the history and significance of this collection, see the digital exhibit, Charles Dickens in the Marketplace.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Whittaker Family Charles Dickens Book Collection
Dickens material in the Vassar College Autograph Files
Subject Headings
Names:
Kyd, 1856 or 7-1937; Browne, Hablot Knight, 1815-1882; Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870--Characters--Illustrations; Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870--Friends and associates
Document Types:
Engravings (prints); Plates (illustrations); Sheet music; Playbills; Watercolors (paintings); Realia
VCL Categories:
Art and Artists; Literature and Writing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, April 2009. Last updated by Emma Gronbeck, June 2025.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Whittaker Family, 2008.
Series List
- Series I. Dickens Biography and Reviews, 1843, 1854
- Series II. Images of Dickens, 1875, undated
- Series III. Correspondence, 1862-1870
- Series IV. Material relating to Dickens' Work, 1838-circa 1860
- Series V. Playbills, [1836?]-1873, 1924
- Series VI. Sheet Music, 1838, circa 1860s, undated
- Series VII. Art and Illustrations, 1831-1992, undated
- Series VIII. Realia and Collectibles, 1912-1993
- Series IX. Miscellaneous Dickensiana, 1846-2003
Container List
- SERIES I. DICKENS BIOGRAPHY AND/OR REVIEWS
  - Brief article regarding American Notes review, National Intelligencer, 1843 Feb 25 (Folder 2.15)
  - "Charles Dickens A Fugitive Bankrupt," New York Semi Weekly, 1854 Aug 4 (Map Case — Drawer 37)
- SERIES II. IMAGES OF DICKENS
  - Watts, Walter Henry. Tinted pencil sketch of Dickens head, with Dickens' signature, undated (Folder 2.1)
  - Hollyer, Samuel (engraver). Engraving of Charles Dickens sitting in his Study at Gadshill, 1875 (Folder 2.2)
  - Hart, H. Blackburn (engraver). Mezzotint engraving after the 1859 portrait by William Powell Frith, undated; (framed) (Framed Storage 2.3)
  - Unknown artist. Print of a pencil drawing, undated; (originally framed with an 1864 personal check signed by Dickens - now included in same folder) (Folder 4.1)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Charles Dickens to Charles W. Kent, 1870 Jun 8; (facsimile) (Folder 5.1)
  - Charles Dickens to Charles W. Kent, 1862 Oct 15; (ALS, envelope and transcription) (Folder 5.2)
  - Charles Dickens to Mr. Armstrong, 1862 May 9; (ALS on All the Year Round stationery, transcription) (Folder 5.3)
- SERIES IV. MATERIAL RELATING TO DICKENS' WORKS
  - Barnaby Rudge, Chapters 19-20, New York Mirror, 1841 May 29 (Folder 2.14)
  - Advertisement for the first bound edition of Oliver Twist, 1838; (1 poster card) (Folder 5.26)
  - Advertisement for the first printing of Little Dorrit, 1857; (1 poster card) (Folder 5. 27)
  - Plates from the Pollock’s Juvenile Drama play set, Oliver Twist or, The Parish Boy’s Progress, (London: B. Pollock), [circa 1860]); (35 prints, including some torn items and several duplicates) (Folder 7.11)
- SERIES V. PLAYBILLS
  - The Strange Gentleman, St. James Theatre, [London], [1836?] Oct; (extremely brittle) (Folder 2.10)
  - Sam Weller! or the Pickwickians, Strand Theatre, London, 1837 Jul (Folder 1.2)
  - Sam Weller! or the Pickwickians, Theatre Royal, Bath, 1837 Dec (Folder 1.3)
  - The Pickwickians, Theatre Royal, Birmingham, 1838 Apr (Folder 2.10)
  - A Christmas Carol, Adelphi Theatre, London, 1844 Jan (Map Case — Drawer 37)
  - Nicholas Nickleby, Boston Theatre, Boston, 1847 Mar (Folder 2.9)
  - Nicholas Nickleby, Boston Museum, Boston, 1849 Jan (Folder 2.9)
  - Savage and the Maiden, National Theatre, [Boston], 1850 May (Folder 2.9)
  - Fortunio and his Seven Gifted Servants(featuring Charles Dickens, Jr. as King Alfourite), Theatre Royal, Tavistock House, 1855 Jan 8; (fabric - torn) (Folder 1.5)
  - original enclosure for Fortunio… (Box 1)
  - Holly-Tree Inn, Standard Theatre, London, [1856] Jan (Folder 2.11)
  - A Christmas Carol, Adelphi Theatre, London, 1860 Jan (Map Case — Drawer 37)
  - Oliver Twist, Howard Athenæum, Boston, 1861 (Folder 1.4)
  - Oliver Twist, Boston Theatre, Boston, 1870 Jan (Folder 2.9)
  - Oliver Twist, The Globe, Boston, 1871 Mar (Folder 2.9)
  - Some Bells That Rang, Britannia Theatre, London, 1873 Mar (Map Case — Drawer 37)
  - Dickens Christmas Pageant, including The Fezziwig Swarry, Milwaukee-Downer College, Milwaukee, WI, 1924 (Folder 5.4)
- SERIES VI. SHEET MUSIC
  - "The Chimes Quadrille, Composed for the Musical Bouquet,", undated (Folder 1.6)
  - Bruton and Allen. "My Dear Old Faithful Doll." London: Charles Jeffreys, undated (Folder 2.3)
  - Caldicott and Oxenford. "Jenny Wren (The Doll's Dressmaker)." London: Patey and Willis, undated (Folder 2.4)
  - Carpenter and Crouch. "The Chimes Song." London: Duff and Hodgson, undated (Folder 1.7)
  - Carpenter and Glover. "What Are The Wild Waves Saying." London: Robert Cocks and Co., undated (Folder 1.8)
  - Glindon and Craven. "The Literary Dustman: A Comic Song." London: T. Purday, undated (Folder 2.5)
  - Godfrey, Dan. "Little Nell: Waltz." London: Chappell and Co., 1860s (Folder 2.6)
  - Lancelot, F. "The Cricket on the Hearth." London: Bingley and Strange, undated (Folder 2.7)
  - Marriott, C. H. R. "Dolly Varden Quadrille." London: Ashdown and Parry, undated (Folder 1.9)
  - Montgomery, W. H. "Little Dorrit's Polka." London: D'Almaine and Co., undated (Folder 1.10)
  - Normann, Jules. "Little Dorrit's Polka." London: Musical Bouquet, undated (Folder 1.11)
  - Roe, John, Jr. "Roe's Pickwickian Quadrilles." London: Duff and Co., undated (Folder 1.12)
  - Russell, Henry. "The Ivy Green, A Ballad." Philadelphia: L. A. Alfred Schmidt, 1838 (Folder 1.13)
  - Van Noorden, P. E. "'All the Year Round' Schottische." London: George Emery and Co., undated (Folder 1.14)
  - Van Noorden, P. E. Little Dorrit's Schottische." London: George Emery and Co., undated (Folder 2.8)
- SERIES VII. ART and ILLUSTRATIONS
  - Barnard, Frederick
    - Character Sketches published by California Art & Engraving Co., circa 1930; (9 prints) (Folder 5.5)
  - Browne, Hablot K. (Phiz)
    - Stiles illustrations — Punch and Judy show, undated; (ink and watercolor) (Folder 4.2)
    - Stiles illustrations — Punch and Judy show with child, undated; (ink and watercolor) (Folder 4.3)
    - Stiles illustrations —"Follow. Follow Me! — Hunting party", undated; (ink and watercolor) (Folder 4.4)
    - Stiles illustrations — Three men, undated; (ink and watercolor) (Folder 4.5)
    - Stiles illustrations — Woman and pig, undated; (ink and watercolor) (Folder 4.6)
    - Stiles illustrations — Woman leaning on stile, undated; (pencil and watercolor) (Folder 4.7)
    - Stiles illustrations — Couple embracing, undated; (pencil and watercolor) (Folder 4.8)
    - Stiles illustrations — Man lifting woman over, with windmill in background, undated; (ink and watercolor) (Folder 4.9)
    - Stiles illustrations — Man lifting woman over, with town in background, undated; (ink and watercolor) (Folder 4.10)
    - Stiles illustrations — Man helping woman, undated; (ink and watercolor) (Folder 4.11)
    - Stiles illustrations — "Farewell Brother Noah, Farewell Sister Rebecca", undated; (ink and watercolor) (Folder 4.12)
    - Plates from Bleak House, unknown edition, but similar to volume 17 of the Gadshill Works of Charles Dickens, undated; (8 plates) (Folder 5.6)
  - Buss, Robert
    - Plates from The Pickwick Papers, unknown edition, undated; (2 plates) (Folder 5.7)
  - Clarke, Joseph Clayton ("Kyd")
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Nell, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.1)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Grandfather Trent, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.2)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Kit, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.3)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Quilp, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.4)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Dick Swiveller, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.5)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — The Single Gentleman, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.6)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Sampson Brass, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.7)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Sally Brass, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.8)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Mrs. Jarley, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.9)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — The Little Marchionesse, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.10)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Mr. Chuckster, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.11)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Jowl, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.12)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Short, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.13)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Codlin, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.14)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — The Old Schoolmaster, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.15)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — The Furnace Man, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.16)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Mr. Vuffin, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.17)
    - Old Curiosity Shop — Slum, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.18)
    - Cover of Character Sketches from Charles Dickens, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.19)
    - Letter from Jerome Kern to Randolph Hearst expressing their mutual interest in the "Kyd" illustrations, [no year] Feb 14; (accompanied Our Mutual Friend watercolor set) (Folder 6.20)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Cover page for set, undated (Folder 6.21)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Jenny Wren, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.22)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Mr. Boffin, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.23)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Mr. Veneering, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.24)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Sloppy, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.25)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Bradley Headstone, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.26)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Mr. Venus, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.27)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Mr. Fledgeby, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.28)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Mr. Podsnap, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.29)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Silas Wegg, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.30)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Rogue Riderhood, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.31)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Mr. Twemlow, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.32)
    - Our Mutual Friend — The Cherub, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.33)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Mr. Dolls, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.34)
    - Our Mutual Friend — Mrs. Todgers [?], undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.35)
    - Our Mutual Friend — [Mr. Riah?], undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.36)
    - Our Mutual Friend — 3 unidentified men, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.37)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Barnaby Rudge, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.38)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — David Copperfield, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.39)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Uriah Heep, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.40)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Oliver Twist, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.41)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Fagin, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.42)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Mr. Bumble, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.43)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Dick Swiveller, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.44)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Mr. Pickwick, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.45)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Tony Weller, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.46)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Sam Weller, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.47)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — The Fat Boy, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.48)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Mr. Pickwick, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.49)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Unidentified man, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 6.50)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Major Bagstock, undated; (watercolor with description sheet) (Folder 6.51)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — The Game Chicken, undated; (watercolor with description sheet) (Folder 6.52)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Rogue Riderhood, undated; (watercolor with description sheet) (Folder 6.53)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Job Trotter, undated; (watercolor with description sheet) (Folder 6.54)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Codlin, undated; (watercolor with description sheet) (Folder 6.55)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Sally Brass, undated; (watercolor with description sheet) (Folder 6.56)
    - Miscellaneous Characters — Fagin, undated; (watercolor with description sheet) (Folder 6.57)
  - Copping, Harold
    - Set of cards showing miscellaneous Dickens scenes and characters. Norfolk, England: Peacock Collection of Holt, undated; (16 cards plus title card) (Folder 5.8)
  - Cruikshank, George
    - Plates from Oliver Twist, most from volumes published by Richard Bentley, London, 1837-1838; (24 items in a portfolio) (Box 1)
    - Plates from Oliver Twist, undated; (10 items) (Folder 5.9)
    - Two engravings from wood blocks engraved by Thomas Williams after designs by Cruikshank. Printed and published by Nicolas McDowall, Old Stile Press, 1992; (No. 24 of 150 copies) (Folder 5.10)
    - Notes, colored sketches, and a bill for copper plates (from J. Yates the engraver) for Cruikshank's illustration of Sketches By Boz., undated; (3 items) (Folder 5.11)
    - Letter to [Jones?] about the "corps" attending church in uniform, 1861 Nov 23 (Folder 5.12)
  - Furniss, Harry
    - Plates [possibly from Charles Dickens Library, vol. 4, Nicholas Nickleby (London: Educational Book Co., 1910)], undated; (3 items) (Folder 5.13)
  - Russell, Walter
    - Unidentified man, undated; (watercolor) (Folder 5.14)
  - Seymour, Robert
    - Invoices for Seymour illustrations, 1831; (2 items) (Folder 5.15)
    - "Sketches by Seymour: A Scramble for Puff Pastry…," S.n., 26 Bride Lane, Fleet Street, [London], undated; (back cover illustration?) (Folder 5.16)
    - "Sketches by Seymour: High Musical Connoisseurs and A Monkey Fancier," William Spooner (for Mrs. Seymour), London, 1839; (print) (Folder 1.1)
  - Miscellaneous and Multiple
    - Plates from The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club, Philadelphia: Carey, Lea and Blanchard, 1838 (Folder 5.17)
    - Silhouettes of Dickens and 19 of his characters. London: Dickens' Old Curiosity Shop, undated; (20 prints) (Folder 5.18)
- SERIES VIII. REALIA and COLLECTIBLES
  - Cigarette Cards
    - Player's — Characters from Dickens, as drawn by Joseph Clayton Clarke (Kyd), [1923?]; (50 cards) (Folder 7.1)
    - R & J Hill —Historic Places from Dickens' Classics — small size, [1926?]; (50 cards) (Folder 7.2)
    - R & J Hill — Historic Places from Dickens' Classics — large size, [1926?]; (50 cards) (Folder 7.3)
    - Cope's — Dickens Character Series, [1939]; (25 cards) (Folder 7.4)
    - Godfrey Phillips — Dickens bust card, no. 41 of a series, undated; (1 card) (Folder 7.5)
  - Tea Cards
    - Brooke Bond — Famous People series — Dickens, no 6 of a series of 50, undated; (1 card) (Folder 7.5)
  - Stamps
    - Charles Dickens Centenary Testimonial Committee — Sheet of stamps created to commemorate the centenary of Dickens' birth, published by Strand Magazine, London and New York, 1912 (Folder 7.6)
    - Kenmore — Charles Dickens: Greatest novelist of All Time — set commemorating the centenary of Dickens' death, 1970 (Folder 7.7)
    - British Post Office —First day covers and stamps commemorating the centenary of Dickens' death, 1970 (Folder 7.8)
    - Fleetwood — Joyous Carols of Christmas —first day covers, 1978; (2 sets) (Folder 7.9)
    - Miscellaneous stamps from a variety of countries, circa 1970-1993 (Folder 7.10)
  - Coins
    - Commemorating the 100th anniversary of the birth Charles Dickens, 1912; (1 brass coin) (Box 8)
    - John Roberts coin commemorating the 100th anniversary of the death Charles Dickens, 1970; (1 silver coin, numbered 00025) (Box 8)
    - Commemorating the 100th anniversary of the death Charles Dickens, 1970; (1 large brass coin) (Box 8)
    - Commemorating the 100th anniversary of the death Charles Dickens, 1970; (3 smaller brass coins) (Box 8)
    - "God Bless Us Every One,", undated; (1 silver coin) (Box 8)
  - Spoons
    - Set of 12 spoons featuring Dickens characters, with accompanying rack. [Franklin Mint], [1981]; (pewter [and plastic?]) (Box 3)
    - Set of 12 spoons featuring characters from "A Christmas Carol," with accompanying rack. [Franklin Mint], undated; (pewter) (Boxes 9 and 17)
  - Ceramics
    - Covered dish featuring Sairey Gamp. New Hall Hanley Pottery, undated; (ceramic) (Box 10)
    - Set of 6 pin dishes featuring Dickens Characters. New Hall Hanley Pottery, undated; (ceramic) (Box 10)
    - Decorative plate with portrait commemorating the centenary of Dickens' death. No. 158 of 5,000. England: Spode, 1970; (bone china) (Box 14)
    - Decorative plate with portrait commemorating the centenary of Dickens' death. No. 1,100 of 5,000. England: Spode, 1970; (bone china) (Box 14)
    - Set of four place settings, including dinner plates, bread and butter plates, salad bowls, cups and saucers. England: EIT [English Ironstone Tableware], undated; (ceramic) (Box 13)
  - Place Mats and Coasters
    - Set of 6 place mats featuring Dickens scenes. England: Pimpernel, undated; (coated cork) (Box 14)
    - Coasters — Set of 6 coasters featuring Dickens scenes. England: Pimpernel, undated; (coated cork) (Box 14)
  - Statuary
    - Bookends — busts of Charles Dickens. NY: Pompeian Bronze Co., undated; (bronze) (Box 15)
    - Door knocker — Charles Dickens' head, undated; (bronze) (Box 15)
    - Statues — Bust of Charles Dickens, undated; (ceramic) (Box 16)
    - Statues — Set of 3 figurines of Dickens characters possibly by Peerage, [1966?]; (brass) (Box 11)
    - Statues — Set of 4 figurines of Dickens characters possibly by Peerage, [1966?]; (brass) (Box 12)
- SERIES IX. MISCELLANEOUS DICKENSIANA
  - Gadshill Place — Particulars and Conditions of Sale of Charles Dickens' home, County of Kent, 1879; (map included) (Folder 2.12)
  - General Theatrical Fund — Advertisement card announcing First Anniversary Festival, 1846 Apr 6 (Folder 5.19)
  - General Theatrical Fund — Broadside announcing First Anniversary Festival, 1846 Apr 6 (Folder 2.13)
  - Dickens-Irving Fellowship Centenary — Letter from Eleanor Roosevelt to [Enid Dickens?] Hawksley, 1937 Dec 7; (1 ALS) (Folder 5.20)
  - Dickens-Irving Fellowship Centenary — invitation to Sarah Herbert to join the committee and come to the dinner, 1937 (Folder 5.21)
  - Macready, William Charles (actor and friend of Charles Dickens) — Illustrated poem: "The King and the Norse King…", undated; (Bound MS, 6 pages) (Folder 5.22)
  - Stonehouse, James. Poem "Addressed to Charles Dickens Esq., on the occasion of his presiding at the Annual Soirée of the Mechanics' Institution, Liverpool, Monday, February 26, 1844", (1 ms draft, 2 edited ts, 1 final ts) (Box 2)
  - Map: "Johnson's England and Wales,", undated (Map Case — Drawer 37)
  - Personal check from Dickens to W. Ring, 1864 (Folder 4.1)
  - Brochure for the George and Vulture, undated (Folder 5.23)
  - Newspaper clippings mentioning Dickens, 1915-2003 (Folder 5.24)
  - Invitation to the California State University Northridge Library's Dickens dinner, 2003 (Folder 5.25)
  - Dickens House — admission ticket and brochure, undated (Folder 5.28)